Guide to the Angola Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Angola collection
1853-2012
MS 1502
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
5.81
(11 boxes)
The collection consists of correspondence, printed material, flags, and photographs relating to the history of Angola and the current political, economic, and social conditions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the African Collection Curator.
Associated Materials
African Collection (MS 605); African Postcard Collection (MS 1575). Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged by accession.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence, printed material, flags, and photographs relating to the history of Angola and the current political, economic, and social conditions.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Angola -- Commerce -- History; Angola -- Description and travel; Angola -- Economic conditions; Angola -- History; Angola -- Politics and government; Angola -- Social conditions; Benguela Province (Angola); Govea, Augustus E. B. (Augustus Edward Bothelho), approximately 1826-1890; Schweitzer, Albert, 1875-1965; Partido Democrático de Angola; Unióao Nacional para a Independæencia Total de Angola
- Original Accession, 1853-1993
  - Augustus E. B. Govea
    - Correspondence concerning trading/shipping company in Luanda, 1853 November 12-1856 December 22, 1857 January 26-1861 February 18, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - Invoices regarding trade and shipping, 1854 June 16-1860 October 10 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letter from George M. Houser, describing his trip to French Equatorial Africa, including a visit to Dr. Albert Schweitzer's hospital and to numerous missions, 1954 September 23 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Relatorio da Actividade de Vasco Valdez, Missão de Biologia Maritima, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Angolan liberation: pamphlets; journals; documents printed in the United States, 1961-1993 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Liberté [et Terre]": printed material published by La Mission du Caire du Gouvernement Révolutionnaire de l'Angola en Exil (GRAE), 1967 January -1970 August (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - National Union for the Total Independence of Angola (UNITA): communiques; papers; documents, 1968-1994 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - Angolan liberation: pamphlets; journals; documents printed internationally, 1970-1994 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "A Voz Democratica de Angola P. D. A.": monthly information bulletin of the Angolan Democratic Party, 1971 April (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Agostinho Neto, Antonio, "Sobre a literatura": discourse for the Instituto Nacional do Livro e do Disco (INALD), 1977 November 24 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Angolan government information journals, 1977-1991 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Angolan women's movement, [1983?]-1985 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Agencia Angola Press (ANGOP): news bulletins, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - "Africa confidencial", 1986 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - "Kwacha News" and other material from the Free Angola Information Service, 1986-1991 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - "Angola Today" and other material from the Free Angola Campaign, 1988-1990 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - "Angola Comment": Catholic Institute for International Relations (CIIR), 1991 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - "Serviços bibliográficos da Livraria Portugal", 1991 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - "Correio da semana: semanário de informação geral", 1992 February (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Direcção dos Caminhos de Ferro de Loanda, Caminho de Ferro de Malange: photographs, Undated (Box 2, Folder 22-24)
- Additional Material, 1950-1992; Accession 1995-M-007
  General note
  Also includes Accession 1995-M-049
  - Movimento Popular de Libertação de Angola (MPLA-Partido do Trabalho): "Programa E Estatutos", 1991 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Partido Angolano Conservador da Identidade Africana (PACIA): "Manifesto", 1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - D.S.O.P.: Repartição Provincial de Benguela Secção Das Estradas Adjuvantes Ad C.F.B.: Relatorio, 1950-1954 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Additional Material, 1965-1993; Accession 1995-M-132
  - Ad Hoc Coalition for a New Foreign Policy [formerly the Coalition to Stop Funding the War, informational fliers], 1975, 1976 January 23, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Africa Fund [Angola information packet and fliers], 1976 Mar, 1994 September 5 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Africa News" [possible radio broadcasts on the Angolan civil war], 1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - African Agenda [a voice of Afro-American opinion, vol. 5, no.1], 1976 December-January (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - African National Congress, "Report: Commission of Inquiry into Recent Developments in the People's Republic of Angola" [two copies], 1984 March 14 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - African Youth Movement for Liberation and Unity [newsletter, vol. 2, nos. 8-9], 1975 July-August (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Agencia Angola Press [ANGOP], 1989 October 27 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - America [publication of the Jesuits of the United States and Canada, vol. 134, no. 14], 1976 April 10 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - American Angolan Public Affairs Council [press releases and fliers], 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - American Committee on Africa [statement opposing U.S. intervention in Angola], 1975, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - American Friends Service Committee [newsletter about daily life in Luanda written by Carole Collins], 1989 May 26 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Americans for Democratic Action [press releases and informational fliers on secret arms shipments to pro-Western forces in Angola], 1975 December 10, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Angola Information Bulletin, 1983 June 1, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Angola News [nos. 22-24], 1995 January 16, February 20, March 15 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Angola Newsletter [publication of United Students for the Liberation of Angola and Southern Africa, vol. 1, no.1], 1976 February (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Angola Peace Fund [APF]
    - APF Speaks... [a periodical of the Angola Peace Fund], 1990 July 4 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - "A policy statement", 1989 June 2 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Angola Peace Monitor [published by ACTSA on behalf of the Angola Emergency Campaign, vol. II, no. 1-vol. III, no. 5], 1995 September 30-1997 January 29 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Angola Solidarity Committee News [nos. 6 and 9], 1976, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Angola: the Possible Peace [published by the Catholic Institute for International Relations], 1991 August (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Angola: the Struggle for Liberation, 1976 February (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Angola Update [newsletter], 1990 April (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Angolan peace process [several documents and statements], 1988-1991 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Association of Concerned African Scholars [press release opposing U.S. aid to UNITA], 1989 May 5 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Campaign for Democratic Foreign Policy [campaign goals and fliers], Udated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Center for National Security Studies, Washington, D.C.
    - "Angola: Reagan's Covert Action Policy VI", 1986 Jan/February (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Intelligence Report [vol. 1, no. 1], Undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Chicago Committee for the Liberation of Angola, Mozambique and Guinea [includes "Angola Alert," nos. 2 and 4, and related materials], 1975 November 22, 1976 January 5, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - CIA [notes and brief reports on Angola], 1975, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Coalition for a New Foreign and Military Policy
    - "Campaign against U.S. Intervention" [legislative update], 1981 June 1, December 1 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - News clippings [on US intervention in Angola], 1975, 1980, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - "Common Cause on Angola", 1976 January 27 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Conference on Angola [notes from speeches made at conference held at Gustavus Adolphus College in St. Peter, Minnesota], 1976 March 26-27 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Congressional Black Caucus [press release demanding end to U.S. Angola intervention], 1975 December 17 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - The Conservative Caucus, Inc., "Background Information on Angola", Undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Cox, Courtland, "The American Involvement in Angola" [paper prepared for the National Black Coalition Against U.S. Involvement in Angola and Southern Africa], 1976 February 6-8 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Davis, Nathaniel, "The Angola Decision of 1975: A Personal Memoir" [photocopy of an article from Foreign Affairs ], Undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Embassy of the Republic of Angola in the United Kingdom [fliers and a press release on meeting of the chiefs of general staff of the Angolan Armed Forces and Unita's military forces], 1995 February 2-3 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - European Parliamentarians for (Southern) Africa [election observers], 1992 September 29-30 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Fenton Communications, Inc., "Jonas Savimbi: The Truth Behind the Myth: Agent of Democracy--or Apartheid?", Undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Friends of Angola, "Russia and the U.S.--Partners in Imperialism" [flier], 1975 October 25 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - The Heritage Foundation
    - "Angola Tests the Reagan Doctrine" [paper in "The Heritage Foundation Backgrounder"], 1985 November 14 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - "The Coming Winds of Democracy in Angola" [The Heritage Lectures, speech by Jonas Savimbi], 1989 October 5 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - International Commission of Enquiry on Mercenaries [a special report on the trial of mercenaries, Luanda, Angola], 1976 June 7-19 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - International Freedom Foundation, "Angola Peace Monitor" [vol. 3, no. 4], 1991 May 10 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Institute for Policy Studies, IPS Transnational Link [no.13], 1976 February (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - MPLA Solidarity Committee [different issues of "Angola Weekly Summary," and other fliers], 1975-1976, undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Parti Democratique de l'Angola (P.D.A)
    - A voz Democratica de Angola [information bulletin], 1965, 1969, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Mondo a Voz Democratica de Angola, 1967, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Patrice Lumumba Coalition [announcing a fundraising program for reconstruction of Angola called Um So Povo], 1976 March 31 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - "Peace Accords for Angola" [prepared with mediation by the Portuguese government], Undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Peoples' Movement for the Liberation of Angola (MPLA)
    - Interview with Dr. Americo Boavida [director of medical assistance services of MPLA], 1970 June (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Interview with the MPLA delegation to the United Nations, 1975 October 18 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - People's Republic of Angola [proclamation of the independence of the People's Republic of Angola], 1975 November 11 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Permanent Mission of the People's Republic of Angola to the United Nations
    - "Angola- today and for ever", 1982 January 25 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Letter from President Joseph Eduardo Dos Santos to U.N. Security Council and other news extracts, 1983, 1987, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Press release and news extracts, 1991 April (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Statement by Ambassador Manuel Pedro Pacavira, [1990?] (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - "Portugal Mainland and Overseas" [fact sheet produced by the Overseas Companies of Portugal], Undated (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Rainbow Lobby [Washington, D.C], 1991 August 8 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - "The Revolt of the Voiceless" [article translated from Africa, Lisbon], 1988 May 11 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Toronto Committee for the Liberation of Southern Africa, "Angola and After" [article by John Saul], Undated (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Transafrica: The Black American Lobby for Africa and the Caribbean [newsletter]
    - "Reagan Requests Repeal of Clark Amendment: Threatens U.S. Objectives in Southern Africa and Relations with other African Countries [news release], 1981 Apr, May 15 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - "House and Senate Differ on U.S. Covert Activities in Angola" [news release], 1981 May 15 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - UAW International Executive Board, "Resolution on Angola", 1976 January 13 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - United States. Congress
    - Committee on Foreign Affairs [statements and proposals in support of increased US role in Angola], 1985 October 4-1986 July 31, undated (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - House Subcommittee on African Affairs [background material and press conference on Angola peace negotiations and U.S. policy], 1989 September 26 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Members of Congress for Peace through Law, 1981 September 23 (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - Proposed bills to control chemicals used in warfare, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Representatives' position statements on the Angolan situation, 1975, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Testimonies, speeches and statements regarding U.S. policy in Angola [position statement on Southern Africa and the Clark Amendment], 1976, 1980, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - United States. Department of Justice [various acts concerning Foreign Agents Registration, Political Propaganda, etc.], 1982 February 16 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Unites States. Department of State [notes, reports and press statements on U.S. interests and concerns in Angola], 1975, 1979, 1985, undated (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - U.S. Labor Party [public statements opposing U.S. involvement in Angola], 1975, undated (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - U.S. policy in Angola [papers and testimony submitted to the subcommittee on African Affairs], 1976, 1982, 1988, 1989, undated (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - U.S. White House Office [briefings, letters, memos, and press conferences on U.S. policy in Angola], 1976, undated (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - The Washington Office on Africa [fliers and position papers concerning U.S. intervention in Angola], 1981 Feb, Apr, May, Sep, Oct, 1987, undated (Box 3, Folder 74)
- Additional Material, 1961-1998; Accession 2000-M-008
  - Africa Hoy [two copies], 1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Angola News [nos. 25-29, 31-35], 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Angolan News Agency, "One Year of South African Occupation" [a dossier complied by ANGOP], 1982 August 23 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Black Survival Press, "The Armed Struggle in Angola", Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - DeConcini, Dennis [US Senator from Arizona, press release and letter to President Reagan urging him to press for a negotiated solution to Angola], 1988 May 12 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Embassy of the Republic of Angola in the U.K. [press releases], 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "A Idade do Bronze", 1995 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Kwacha News [the official newsletter of the Free Angola Information Service], 1988 Jan, 1991 Jan/February (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Liberation [No. 13], 1989 Mar/April (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - National Unity for the Total Independence of Angola (UNITA) [official statements and speeches by Dr. Savimbi], 1998, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "Premier Salazar [of Portugal] Speaks Out on Angola", 1961 May 31 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Additional Material, 1984-2000, undated; Accession 2010-M-092
  - People's Movement for the Liberation of Angola pamphlet, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Democracy fact-file (Angola), 2000 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Parting Company: Newsletter of people against Rio Tinto Zinc and subsidiaries, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correio da semana, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Additional material, 1960-2012; Accession 2015-M-001
  - Printed material, 1960s-2012 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Flags, Circa 2000s (Box 2)
  - Posters, Circa 2000s (Box 3, Folder 1)